<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="tv/tv.xsl" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>PEMBROKE 25: Description of the Manuscript and Context of its Production</title>
                <author>Rebecca Rushforth</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2008-04-04T09:04:00</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <name>Dot Porter</name>
                <date>2008-04-04T09:04:00</date>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Description of the Manuscript</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Codicological Description</head>
                    <p>The manuscript as it now stands consists of 181 parchment folios, plus two
                        modern paper flyleaves at each end. Each page is approximately 315 mm x 205
                        mm. It is bound in a nineteenth-century binding, which is in need of repair,
                        on five medieval sewing-stations.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Quires</head>
                        <p>The manuscript is arranged in twenty-three quires as follows: a singleton
                            (fol. 1), I<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 2–9), II<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                            (fols. 10–17), III<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 18–25), IV<hi rend="sup"
                                >8</hi> (fols. 26–33), V<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 34–41), VI<hi
                                rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 42–49), VII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols.
                            50–57), VIII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 58–65), IX<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                            (fols. 66–73), X<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 74–81), XI<hi rend="sup"
                            >8</hi> (fols. 82–89), XII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 90–97), XIII<hi
                                rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 98–105), XIV<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols.
                            106–13), XV<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 114–21), XVI<hi rend="sup"
                            >8</hi> (fols. 122–29), XVII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 130–37),
                                XVIII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 138–45), XIX<hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                            (fols. 146–53), XX<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 154–61), XXI<hi
                                rend="sup">4</hi> (fols. 162–65), XXII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols.
                            166–73), XXIII<hi rend="sup">8</hi> (fols. 174–81). In short, the
                            manuscript consists entirely of regular quires of eight, with two small
                            exceptions: it starts with a singleton, and the twenty-first quire is a
                            quire of only four leaves, two bifolia. M. R. James thought that the
                            first quire had once contained five sheets, making ten leaves, and that
                            the pair to fol. 1, which would have come between fols. 9 and 10, had
                            been excised. I think it more likely, given the regularity of the rest
                            of the manuscript and the fact that no text is missing between fols. 9
                            and 10, that fol. <ref target="IMT/1r/1r.htm">1</ref> was added to the
                            manuscript in the mid-twelfth century to enlarge the blank space
                            available for the addition of historical material. (On this added
                            historical material, <ref type="page" target="#flyleaves">see
                            below</ref>.) James suggests that the note on <ref
                                target="IMT/1r/1r.htm">1r</ref> is only the end of a longer text; if
                            this were true, fol. 1 would be the last leaf of an added quire.</p>
                        <p> The sheets within the quires are almost without exception arranged HFFH,
                            so that within each opening either both verso and recto are the hair
                            side of the parchment or both are the flesh side. This was good practice
                            in medieval book production because the hair side of the parchment was
                            usually darker than the flesh side and showed follicles, while the flesh
                            side might be greasier and have vein patterning. (Early Insular
                            techniques of parchment preparation, however, rendered this arrangement
                            unnecessary by producing a hair and flesh side which were very difficult
                            to tell apart.) The parchment in Pembroke 25 is of a practical quality,
                            rather than being highly prepared. It is quite stiff; the hair-side is
                            yellow-brown with clearly visible follicles; the flesh-side is paler and
                            often shows a pattern of veining (<ref>image</ref>), typically caused by
                            inadequate draining of blood from the animal’s body at slaughter,
                            leaving a residue of iron to react with chemicals used later in the
                            parchmenting process. Some folios, made from the edge of the skin, lack
                            their lower corners. Many slits, tears, or holes in the parchment have
                            been mended with chamfered patches or sewing, sometimes in colored
                            thread. The impression left is of a workmanlike book, not high-status,
                            but practical in its construction.</p>
                        <p> The one exception to the arrangement of hair facing hair and flesh
                            facing flesh occurs in the thirteenth quire, where the second sheet of
                            the quire, fols. 99 and 104, is arranged with hair outwards instead of
                            inwards. This means that in the openings of <ref
                                target="IMT/98v/98v.htm">98v</ref>–<ref target="IMT/99r/99r.htm"
                            >99r</ref>, <ref target="IMT/99v/99v.htm">99v</ref>–<ref
                                target="IMT/100r/100r.htm">100r</ref>, <ref
                                target="IMT/103v/103v.htm">103v</ref>–<ref
                                target="IMT/104r/104r.htm">104r</ref>, and <ref
                                target="IMT/104v/104v.htm">104v</ref>–<ref
                                target="IMT/105r/105r.htm">105r</ref>, hair faces flesh or vice
                            versa. However, in this quire the hair and flesh sides of the parchment
                            are much more alike than elsewhere in the book, and the contrast in the
                            openings is hardly noticeable. This similarity presumably led to a
                            mistake by the scribe.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Ruling</head>
                        <p>The manuscript is written in a single column, fols. 1–165 in 28 lines,
                            and fols. 166–73 in 27 lines. <ref target="IMT/174r/174r.htm">174r</ref>
                            was ruled for 28 lines, but only 27 were written, and from <ref
                                target="IMT/175r/175r.htm">175r</ref> to the end of the manuscript
                            there are 27 ruled lines per page. These were ruled drypoint before the
                            parchment was folded. The prickings in the outer margin seem to have
                            been made with a triangular point. The size of the writing area is
                            approximately 250 x 145 mm, with 9–10 mm between ruled lines, and with a
                            double vertical bounding line ruled to provide space for litterae
                            notabiliores. On occasion the gap between lines is not regular, for
                            example on fol. <ref target="IMT/180r/180r.htm">180</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head> Ink</head>
                        <p>The ink is shiny and black; this is more typical of the Anglo-Saxon than
                            the Continental tradition at this time. <emph>Litterae
                            notabiliores</emph> have been picked out in red (<ref>image</ref>).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Gold Flecks</head>
                        <p>An odd feature of this manuscript is that tiny spots of gold can be seen
                            on several pages, e.g. 000 (<ref>image</ref>). These are on top of the
                            script. They are not regular at all and play no decorative role in the
                            manuscript. One possible explanation for their appearance is that the
                            manuscript was being made in the same environment as a much more complex
                            and high-grade project involving gilding, and particles of gold leaf
                            either became air-borne and landed on the manuscript or were transferred
                            to it through human contact. Another possibility is that the manuscript
                            was used to store gold leaf, and some small flecks were not successfully
                            removed.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Marks of provenance</head>
                    <p>The manuscript contains several marks of provenance assigning it to Bury St
                        Edmunds abbey in Suffolk. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>‘Liber S. Edmundi’</head>
                        <p>The manuscripts of Bury St Edmunds were exposed to a number of helpful
                            campaigns by librarians of the institution. As a result, there are
                            several different ways to identify a manuscript from Bury. Pembroke 25
                            contains a late twelfth- or early thirteenth-century Bury St Edmunds
                            ownership inscription at the top of <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm">3r</ref>
                            that reads “Liber sancti Edmundi regis et martyris”. This inscription is
                            found in a number of other Bury St Edmunds books, including Pembroke
                            College manuscripts 23 and 24 (<ref>image</ref>). It shows that Pembroke
                            25 was part of Bury St Edmunds’ main working library collection at that
                            date, since the manuscripts so marked are mostly working books for
                                monks.<hi><note place="foot" n="1">Rouse and Rouse pp. xliii–xliv list
                                    Pembroke MSS 17, 18, 24 (Latin homilies), 25, 26, 47, 49, 59,
                                    84, 88, Bodl. e Mus. 31, to which can be added 23 (Latin
                                    homilies), 81, Cotton Julius E. VII (Old English homilies), and
                                    no doubt many others. CHECK SHARPE’s article</note>
                            </hi>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Henry of Kirkestede, Bury Librarian</head>
                        <p>The manuscript also contains annotations by Bury St Edmunds’ great
                            medieval librarian, Henry of Kirkstede, sometimes known as Boston of
                                Bury.<hi><note place="foot" n="2">Rouse and Rouse.</note>
                            </hi> His work in Pembroke 25 corresponds to his usual pattern of
                            activity and involves three different types of addition: an <emph>ex
                                libris</emph>, a contents list, and a classmark.<hi><note place="foot" n="3">Rouse and Rouse, pp. xliii-li, esp. p.
                                    xliv.</note>
                            </hi>
                        </p>
                        <p> Kirkestede found an <emph>ex libris</emph> inscription already in place
                            on <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm">3r</ref>, written in the late twelfth or
                            early thirteenth century as discussed above. He added to it the words
                            “in quo continentur omelie ^uel sermones^ xcv . item tractatus alani
                            porrei de arte praedicandi.” Kirkestede felt the need to expand the
                                <emph>ex libris</emph> to include a brief summary of contents, and
                            this might suggest that, in this case at least, he dealt with the
                                <emph>ex libris </emph>before he decided to add a detailed contents
                            list on the facing page. The second item is to be identified with the
                                <emph>Summa de arte praedicandi</emph> written by Alanus ab Insula,
                            also known as Alain of Lille (<emph>ca</emph>. 1128–1203), which
                            suggests that the manuscript was composite at this time.</p>
                        <p> As was his usual practice, Kirkestede wrote a contents list on <ref
                                target="IMT/2v/2v.htm">2v</ref> that reads as follows:</p>
                        <p>Liber monachorum sancti edmundi in quo continentur<lb/>Omelie uel
                            sermones . xcv . ab adventu deum usque ad festum sancti andree . et de
                            apostolis . martyribus . confessoribus . et uirginibus . et de
                            dedicacione ecclesie<lb/>Rabanus de officio misse et eius misterio et de
                            significacione canonicarum horarum .</p>
                        <p>This list repeats the <emph>ex libris</emph> information, although
                            Kirkestede’s preferred form was to refer to the book as a possession of
                            the monks of St Edmund, rather than of the saint himself.<hi><note place="foot" n="4">Rouse and Rouse, p. xliv.</note>
                            </hi> In contrast to the note on <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm">3r</ref>,
                            this contents list does not mention the <emph>Summa</emph> of Alanus ab
                            Insula. The contents list also does not mention the extra sermons, on
                            particular themes rather than about particular occasions, at the end of
                            the volume.</p>
                        <p> Kirkestede also gave the volume a classmark. He devised a system whereby
                            each book in the Bury St Edmunds library had a two-part classmark
                            consisting of a letter and an arabic numeral. (This is quite an early
                            use of Arabic numbers in England.) These classmarks are easily
                            recognized, and are very useful in the reconstruction of the Bury
                            library. Books from other libraries survive with classmarks in a similar
                            format, but in the Bury manuscripts the letter of the classmark always
                            corresponds to its contents, e.g. “B” for “Biblia.” The arabic number
                            makes the classmark unique, but it is not clear whether the numbers were
                            originally serial and continuous, or whether Kirkestede left some
                            numbers empty for further accessions. If they were continuous, then
                            adding up the highest surviving number in each letter allows the Bury
                            library to be estimated as containing around 2000 manuscripts in
                            Kirkestede’s time, of which 218 survive.<hi rend="sup">
                                <note place="foot" n="5">Sharpe, ‘Reconstructing’.</note>
                            </hi> As well as marking these classmarks within the manuscript,
                            Kirkestede seems, from exiguous binding evidence, to have put them on
                            the outside of the manuscript, presumably to make them more easily
                            findable.</p>
                        <p> In addition to designating classmarks for the manuscripts, Henry of
                            Kirkestede presumably must have also made a library catalogue that
                            listed the books. Unfortunately such a catalogue does not survive.
                            Without this evidence it is not clear what implications the classmarks
                            have for the physical storage of the manuscripts.<hi><note place="foot" n="6">Sharpe, ‘Reconstructing’, pp. 206–7.</note>
                            </hi> The existence of some volumes containing two different classmarks
                            implies that the classmark did not necessarily relate directly to where
                            they were kept.<hi><note place="foot" n="7">Sharpe, ‘Reconstructing’, p. 213.</note>
                            </hi> Possibly it indicated a particular <emph>armarium</emph> or book
                            closet, which could have been shared by manuscripts of more than one
                            letter.</p>
                        <p> Kirkestede gave Pembroke 25 the classmark “O.55,” where the “O” stands
                            for “Omeliae.” He wrote this classmark on both <ref
                                target="IMT/2v/2v.htm">2v</ref> and <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm"
                            >3r</ref>. This puts the manuscript in a class that also contains works
                            of Origen. Other surviving volumes of homilies in this class are
                            Kirkestede’s O.52 and O.54, now classed as Pembroke College manuscripts
                            23 and 24.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Sixteenth-Century Round Hand</head>
                        <p>Another contents note was added on <ref target="IMT/2v/2v.htm">2v</ref>
                            in a round hand, probably from the sixteenth century:</p>
                        <p>Homiliae usque festum S. Andrea, de Apostolis martyribus confessoribus et
                            uirginibus, et dedicatione Ecclesiae<lb/>Rabanus Maurus de officio missa
                            et mysterio et horis canonicis<lb/>Magistri Alani summa (uerbum
                            abbreviatum dicta)</p>
                        <p>By the side of the note on Hrabanus Maurus a hand of similar date has
                            written “non occurrit his tractatus.” This hand has not been identified.
                            It may be that of William Smarte or a previous secular owner, or it
                            might be that of a fellow of Pembroke College.</p>
                        <div><head>William Smarte and Pembroke College</head>
                        <p> On <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm">3r</ref>, above the medieval <emph>ex
                                libris</emph> inscription, has been added in a round hand “Liber
                            sociorum Aulee Pembroke ex dono Gulielmi Smarte Aldermani Gyponicens
                            1599.” William Smarte was from a prosperous Ipswich family and became
                            Portman, bailiff, and member of parliament for the city.<hi><note place="foot" n="8">Blatchly, <emph>The Town Library of
                                    Ipswich</emph>, pp. 1–8.</note>
                            </hi> He seems to have played a prominent role in local life; in the
                            famine of 1586 he seized food intended for troops garrisoned in the
                            Netherlands to alleviate the conditions in Ipswich. William owned a
                            number of manuscripts from Bury St Edmunds Abbey which are now at
                            Pembroke College, Cambridge. According to Foxe, William’s father Richard
                            was a staunch Catholic, involved in the persecution of Protestants under
                            Mary, although he repented after her death. Assuming that under Henry
                            VIII and Edward VI Richard’s loyalties had been to the old Catholic ways
                            rather than tempered to suit the times, then perhaps William inherited
                            volumes which his father obtained from Bury St Edmunds at its
                            dissolution in 1539.</p>
                        <p> William Smarte’s will of January 1598/9 left all his Latin books,
                            printed and handwritten, to the church of St Mary Tower in Ipswich, to
                            be kept there for the use of preachers. Before his death in September of
                            the same year, however, he had given all his manuscripts except for a
                            handful to Pembroke College, Cambridge, whose Master at the time was the
                            theologian Lancelot Andrewes. (From the inscription’s date of 1599 one
                            would assume the gift was later than March of that year.) He was
                            persuaded to do this by a fellow of that college, Richard Buckenham, a
                            local man whose family had close connections with the Smartes. It was
                            presumably also through Buckenham’s influence that Smarte set up a
                            number of scholarships to send boys from Ipswich Grammar School to
                            Pembroke College.<hi><note place="foot" n="9">
                                    <emph>Ibid</emph>.</note>
                            </hi>
                        </p>
                        <p> Unfortunately the donations of William Smarte to Pembroke College were
                            not immediately treated with the respect they deserved, and there were
                            losses from the collection. Matthew Wren listed 79 items of Smarte’s
                            donation in his catalogue of the Pembroke manuscripts published in 1617,
                            and lamented that Richard Buckenham had not thought to catalogue them:
                            ‘si catalogum datorum nobis reliquisset, egregium fidem praestissiset.
                            Dedit enim praeter hos proculdubio non paucos qui nunc (proh dolor)
                                absunt.”<hi><note place="foot" n="10">Wren 1617? check James.</note>
                            </hi> For example, a manuscript of Alexander Nequam which had moved to
                            the Bodleian Library by 1620, where it is now MS Bodley 356
                            (<emph>S.C.</emph> 2716), was possibly given as early as 1601 in
                            response to one of Sir Thomas Bodley’s early donation drives. Other
                            manuscripts have also strayed <hi>comment check cat</hi>
                            <hi>.</hi>.</p></div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Script of Pembroke 25</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>English Caroline Minuscule</head>
                        <p> The script of Pembroke 25 is a form of Standard Late English Caroline
                            Minuscule, also known as Style IV Anglo-Caroline minuscule. Caroline
                            minuscule was invented around the late eighth century in Francia,
                            combining elements from Cursive Half-Uncial and local minuscules to
                            produce a clear, elegant script with fewer ligatures and variant letter
                                forms.<hi><note place="foot" n="11">Bischoff, <emph>Latin Palaeography</emph>,
                                    pp. 112–27.</note>
                            </hi> Its association with the court of Charlemagne gives it its modern
                            name. Typical features include the <hi>a</hi> like a modern printed
                                <hi>a</hi>, with an arched top stroke over the round body;
                            <hi>g</hi> like a formal printed <hi>g</hi>, with a round top bowl above
                            a tail (which may have been open or closed); <hi>r</hi> like a modern
                                <hi>r</hi>; and <hi>s</hi> much like a modern <hi>f</hi> but without
                            the cross bar and not descending below the line. This style of script
                            usually has a neat, restrained aspect.</p>
                        <p> Caroline minuscule spread quickly through much of Western Europe but was
                            not taken up in England in the ninth century even though the importation
                            of books in Caroline minuscule and Continental scholars to the court of
                            King Alfred would have been an obvious occasion for this to occur.
                            Caroline minuscule was first written in England in the middle of the
                            tenth century.<hi><note place="foot" n="12">On English Caroline see Bishop,
                                    <emph>ECM</emph>; Dumville, <emph>ECS</emph>; Rushforth,
                                    ‘English Caroline Minuscule’.</note>
                            </hi> It quickly became closely associated with the Benedictine Reform
                            movement promoted by Sts Dunstan, Æthelwold, and Oswald, and King Edgar
                            in the 960s and 970s. Two styles of English Caroline script have been
                            identified from the first half century of its existence. Style I
                            involves writing Caroline minuscule to make it as indistinguishable as
                            possible from that written on the Continent, and it is particularly
                            associated with St Æthelwold. Style II retains some Insular features and
                            is associated with St Dunstan. In the first two decades of the eleventh
                            century, elements from both of these scripts were combined, probably at
                            Canterbury, to produce a typically English script known as Standard Late
                            English Caroline, or Style IV Anglo-Caroline minuscule. This script
                            spread throughout England and has been seen as “a badge of
                                Englishness.”<hi><note place="foot" n="13">Dumville, <emph>ECS</emph>, p, 138</note>
                            </hi> It survived for about half a century after the Norman Conquest in
                            some houses. </p>
                        <p> The characteristic features of Standard Late English Caroline Minuscule
                            are usually taken from the hand of Eadwig Basan, whose work represents
                            the apogee of this style.<hi><note place="foot" n="14">On Eadwig Basan see Bishop,
                                    <emph>ECM</emph>; Dumville, <emph>ECS</emph>; Heslop, ‘The
                                    Production’; Pfaff, ‘Eadui Basan’; Gameson, ‘The Colophon’;
                                    Gameson, <emph>The Scribe Speaks?</emph>; Rankin, ‘An Early
                                    Eleventh-Century Missal Fragment’; Rushforth, ‘English Caroline
                                    Minuscule’; Rushforth, ‘The Prodigal Fragment’.</note>
                            </hi> The script is usually round and elegant, restrained and inactive
                            in aspect. It has wedges on ascenders and at minim-height and also
                            usually has small finishers or feet at the baseline which help give a
                            sense of thick/thin contrast. The enclosed parts of both <hi>a</hi> and
                                <hi>e</hi> are small and narrow, and <hi>a</hi> might sometimes be
                            written so that the arched top stroke extends upwards above
                            minim-height. The form of <hi>g</hi> has a short descending stroke
                            linking the round upper body to the tail, although in later examples
                            this line is sometimes omitted completely and a clear gap is left
                            between the two parts. The top part of <hi>r</hi> is sharply zig-zagged;
                            in later specimens the right-hand or top part of the letter might join
                            the stem quite low down near the baseline, leading to a “split”
                            appearance so that the letter looks a bit like a very narrow <hi>v</hi>.
                            The form of <hi>s</hi> has a heavy shoulder at minim-height. The
                                <hi>c</hi>+<hi>t</hi> ligature is often very close and
                            “loaf-shaped.” Features like two sorts of <hi>r</hi>+<hi>a</hi> ligature
                            (with Caroline <hi>a</hi> and with “cc” <hi>a</hi>), small majuscule
                                <hi>N</hi>, and small majuscule <hi>H</hi> (particularly in the
                                <emph>ihc</emph> abbreviation for <emph>Iesus</emph>) are also
                            typical of this script. In the hands of a master practitioner — such as
                            the aforementioned Eadwig Basan, as well as the mid-eleventh-century
                            scribe of a Canterbury Pontifical (Cambridge, Corpus Christi College
                            44), some scribes at Exeter in the third quarter of the eleventh
                                century,<hi><note place="foot" n="15">On the Exeter scriptorium, 1050–1072, see
                                    Drage, ‘Bishop Leofric’.</note>
                            </hi> and the two Bury scribes who wrote a gospel book at the end of the
                            eleventh century (Cambridge, St John’s College, C. 23 (73)) — it is a
                            supremely elegant and beautiful script. However, when written
                            inexpertly, it can easily appear clumsy, almost cartoonishly
                            exaggerated, stalled, and ragged.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Two Hands of Pembroke 25</head>
                        <p>In the continuum of performances of Standard Late English Caroline
                            Minuscule, the script of Pembroke 25 is to be placed at the high end of
                            the middle. The script is quite attractive, but not highly calligraphic.
                            It is written in an undisciplined, workmanlike fashion. As with other
                            aspects of the manuscript’s production, the script gives a clear
                            impression that the first concern has been to produce a straightforward,
                            usable book.</p>
                        <p> More than one scribe is at work in this manuscript, but exact
                            identification of stints is complicated by the undisciplined nature of
                            the writing. Major writing habits remain constant, while small habits
                            and the aspect of the script change gradually over time. (Similar shifts
                            in writing habits can be paralleled in other manuscripts written at Bury
                            St Edmunds at this period, for example in London, British Library, Royal
                            7. C. ii, where the scribe unsuccessfully attempts to eradicate
                            descending <hi>s</hi> from his work on fol. 167.) I have not been able
                            to identify the change in hand which M. R. James located between his
                            items 34 and 35. However, there is a change in hand between <ref
                                target="IMT/89v/89v.htm">89v</ref> and <ref target="IMT/90r/90r.htm"
                                >90r</ref>, corresponding with a change in quire, but not in text.
                            The difference between these two hands is not a consistent difference of
                            habit, but a difference of aspect and pen: the first hand is large,
                            dense, and round, written flowingly with quite a thick pen, while the
                            second is written slightly smaller and less fluently with a thinner pen.
                            Since these hands are otherwise very similar, I shall refer to them
                            together in the following full description of the script of Pembroke 25.</p>
                        <p> The aspect of both hands is quite dense on the page and round, though
                            these features are more marked in the first hand. Both hands have
                            suggestions of a slight forward lean. Ascenders have tapering wedges,
                            and minims have small wedges. At the baseline there are small, slightly
                            slanted feet or occasionally very small turned-back descenders; full
                            descenders usually turn back a little. </p>
                        <p><hi>a</hi> exhibits the Caroline form with quite a large compartment; it
                            is sometimes tall in initial position, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/56v/56v.htm">56v</ref>9 <hi>a</hi>
                            <emph>utem</emph>. It often has an emphatic top arch, leaning to the
                            left, in a form one might call “quiffed,” e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/8r/8r.htm">8r</ref>22 <hi>a</hi><emph>nima</emph>, <ref
                                target="IMT/90v/90v.htm">90v</ref>24
                                <hi>a</hi><emph>liquas</emph>.<hi><note place="foot" n="16">While Neil Ker referred to this form as
                                    “tall <hi>a</hi>”, David Dumville has used the term “tall
                                    <hi>a</hi>” to refer to the <hi>a</hi> which is simply higher
                                    than minim-height; to avoid confusion I prefer to use a term
                                    which draws attention to the characteristic aspect of this form,
                                    given by the emphatic top-stroke which is particularly dense on
                                    the right-hand side while leaning out to the left of the
                                letter.</note>
                            </hi> At line-end or sometimes word-end, <hi>a</hi> often has an
                            upwards-flicking hair-line finisher. Very occasionally round rather than
                            Caroline <hi>a</hi> appears, e.g. <ref target="IMT/85r/85r.htm"
                            >85r</ref>24–25 <emph>f</emph><hi>a</hi><emph>ce/re</emph>.</p>
                        <p>Both straight-backed <hi>d</hi> and round-backed <hi>d</hi> occur
                            frequently. In the round-backed form the letter often does not rise much
                            above minim-height and has a very small ascending part, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/131r/131r.htm">131r</ref>24
                            <emph>aliqui</emph><hi>d</hi>.</p>
                        <p><hi>e</hi> has a medium-sized, slightly slanting compartment and
                            occasionally a hooked back. There are four different types of
                            <hi>e</hi>-caudata: one with a hooked tail, e.g. 000 (<ref>image</ref>);
                            one with a spurred tail, e.g. <ref target="IMT/39v/39v.htm">39v</ref>11
                                <emph>pręceptum</emph>; one with a looped tail, e.g. 000
                            (<ref>image</ref>); and one with a short lightning-stroke descender
                            slanting down to the left from the bottom-left of the letter, e.g. 000
                                (<ref>image</ref>). On rare occasions two different types of
                            <hi>e</hi>-caudata are used in a single word, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/14v/14v.htm">14v</ref>2 <emph>ęuę</emph>. The <hi>æ</hi>
                            digraph is also found with some frequency, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/165r/165r.htm">165r</ref>25
                                <emph>h</emph><hi>æ</hi><emph>c</emph>.</p>
                        <p><hi>f</hi> has the Caroline form; it has either a little tailed-back
                            descender at the baseline or a small foot. Occasionally Insular
                            minuscule <hi>f</hi> is used to avoid a descender from the line above,
                            e.g. <ref target="IMT/54r/54r.htm">54r</ref>28
                            <hi>f</hi><emph>inem</emph>. <hi>g</hi> has the Caroline form; between
                            bowl and tail it usually has a small stem stroke which often slants to
                            the left. Occasionally bowl and tail are separated by a gap, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/42v/42v.htm">42v</ref>26
                                <emph>di</emph><hi>g</hi><emph>netur</emph>; the tail is sometimes
                            open, sometimes closed with a hair-line. Small majuscule <hi>H</hi> is
                            sometimes used, as is small majuscule <hi>N</hi>. <hi>r</hi> is sharp,
                            sometimes split, e.g. <ref target="IMT/8r/8r.htm">8r</ref>24
                                <hi>r</hi><emph>egis</emph>; occasionally it descends a little.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi>s</hi> has either a heavy shoulder or just a spur; it often has a
                            small tailed-back descender, but occasionally a foot. Ascender-height
                            round <hi>s</hi> is sometimes found at line-end, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/165r/165r.htm">165r</ref>28
                            <emph>caeli</emph><hi>s</hi>. A <hi>v</hi>-shaped form of <hi>u</hi> is
                            occasionally used, e.g. <ref target="IMT/55v/55v.htm">55v</ref>19
                                <hi>v</hi><emph>enit</emph>. <hi>x</hi> usually does not descend
                            below the line. <hi>y</hi> is curved or straight limbed and always
                            dotted. <hi>z</hi> is either minim-height and uncrossed, minim-height
                            and crossed (e.g. <ref target="IMT/56v/56v.htm">56v</ref>24
                                <emph>La</emph><hi>z</hi><emph>are</emph>), or slightly tall and
                            uncrossed (e.g. <ref target="IMT/99r/99r.htm">99r</ref>15–16
                                <emph>bapti/</emph><hi>z</hi><emph>etur</emph>). A descending form
                            of <hi>z</hi> is used once, <ref target="IMT/25v/25v.htm">25v</ref>23
                                <emph>bapti</emph><hi>z</hi><emph>ari</emph>. The
                            <hi>c</hi>+<hi>t</hi> ligature is quite close, and the ligaturing stroke
                            does not rise very high, e.g. <ref target="IMT/6v/6v.htm">6v</ref>10
                                <emph>inta</emph><hi>ct</hi><emph>a</emph> (<ref>image</ref>).
                                <hi>r</hi>+<hi>t</hi> and <hi>s</hi>+<hi>t</hi> ligatures are also
                            used. The <hi>r</hi>+<hi>a</hi> ligature with “cc” form of <hi>a</hi> is
                            found, and the <hi>r</hi> in this ligature often descends below the
                            line, e.g. <ref target="IMT/37r/37r.htm">37r</ref>9
                                <emph>sinist</emph><hi>ra</hi>, <ref target="IMT/180r/180r.htm"
                            >180r</ref>23 <emph>cete</emph><hi>ra</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The abbreviation for <emph>Iesus</emph> sometimes has a small majuscule
                                <hi>H</hi>, e.g. <ref target="IMT/117r/117r.htm">117r</ref>5
                                <emph>Iesu</emph>. The Insular abbreviations for <emph>est</emph>
                            (÷) and <emph>enim</emph> are used, the latter in the form much like a
                            small majuscule <hi>H</hi> without protruding cross bar, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/127v/127v.htm">127v</ref>1 <emph>enim</emph>. The
                            abbreviation mark is usually a horizontal line but is sometimes jagged
                            like a lightning strike, e.g. <ref target="IMT/151r/151r.htm"
                            >151r</ref>12 <emph>spiritus sancti</emph>. The tironian <emph>et</emph>
                            nota is occasionally used, e.g. <ref target="IMT/57v/57v.htm">57v</ref>5
                                <emph>et</emph>, <ref target="IMT/115r/115r.htm">115r</ref> 28
                                <emph>et</emph>. The question mark is used, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/8r/8r.htm">8r</ref>13 <emph>tui?</emph>.</p>
                        <p> Major initials are drawn entirely in red, two or three lines high.
                                <emph>Litterae notabiliores</emph> are drawn from the various
                            majuscule options, <emph>viz</emph>. Uncial, Rustic Capitals, and Square
                            Capitals; variation is seen in the form chosen. They are often picked
                            out in red ink, with one downward stroke of red highlighting an
                            important stroke of the letter. In places rough paragraph marks are also
                            added in red. The same red is used for rubrics. These are written in
                            mixed majuscules, with Rustic Capital forms predominating, e.g. <ref
                                target="IMT/125r/125r.htm">125r</ref>1. However, sometimes primarily
                            Uncial forms are used, e.g. <ref target="IMT/3r/3r.htm">3r</ref>2 and
                                <ref target="IMT/166r/166r.htm">166r</ref>1–2. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>A Palaeographical Dating for Pembroke 25</head>
                    <p>There has not yet been sufficient study of the development of English
                        Caroline minuscule over the course of the eleventh century. Neither of the
                        two major monographs on the script address this issue thoroughly. T. A. M.
                        Bishop’s <emph>English Caroline Minuscule</emph> is necessarily
                        circumscribed by its particular format, and Bishop chose to represent far
                        more manuscripts from the tenth century, during the script’s introduction
                        and early development in England, than from the eleventh. Likewise David
                        Dumville, in his <emph>English Caroline Script and Monastic History</emph>,
                        concentrates on the early years of English Caroline, though he does discuss
                        the first quarter of the eleventh century in detail. Otherwise,
                        palaeographical scholarship has focused on the Norman Caroline minuscule
                        which was introduced after the Conquest in 1066, and English Caroline
                        minuscule of this period has largely been defined in contrast to it. Neil
                        Ker’s invaluable <emph>English Manuscripts in the Century After the Norman
                            Conquest</emph> is the best survey of this period. Ker describes the
                        “beautiful eleventh-century English script, in whose history the Norman
                        Conquest was only a disturbing incident” as “perfectly upright, fairly
                        large, and widely spaced.” The features which Ker thought would stand out as
                        odd to the Norman reader include “the amply curving head of <hi>a</hi>, the
                        larger form of <hi>a</hi> used commonly at the beginning of a word, the bold
                        ligature for <hi>et</hi>, and the handsome <hi>g</hi> with a sharp angle in
                        the stroke connection the upper and lower parts of the letter,” as well as
                        the <hi>r</hi>+<hi>a</hi> and <hi>r</hi>+<hi>t </hi>ligatures and the
                        Insular <emph>autem</emph> abbreviation. Ker also examines the script of
                        this period in his article on the early manuscripts of Salisbury Cathedral.
                        He talks in particular about the “bad habits” of eleventh-century script
                        which a Norman master might wish to eradicate, including:</p>
                    <p><list><item>writing a hyphen at the beginning of a line as well as at the end;</item> <item>making an
                            <emph>rt</emph> ligature;</item> <item>making the <emph>et</emph> ligature in the
                        middle or at the beginning of a word;</item> <item>using rounded <emph>d</emph> as an
                        alternative to upright <emph>d</emph>, not solely in order to save space;</item>
                        <item>writing <emph>ae</emph> or <emph>æ</emph> instead of <emph>ę</emph>;</item>
                        <item>allowing <emph>f</emph>, <emph>r</emph>, and <emph>s</emph>, one, two, or
                        three of them, to fall below the line;</item> <item>using round <emph>s</emph>;</item> <item>making a
                        special form of <emph>a</emph> after <emph>r</emph> [the
                        <hi>r</hi>+<hi>a</hi> ligature with “cc” <hi>a</hi>];</item> <item>using peculiar forms
                        of abbreviation for <emph>autem</emph> and <emph>enim</emph> [the old
                        Insular forms];</item> <item>finishing minims with horizontal feet or serifs . . . the
                        last three are characteristic of older English not older Norman script.<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="17">Ker, ‘The Beginnings’, p. 28</note>
                        </hi></item></list>
                    </p>
                    <p>David Dumville has also commented on post-Conquest script from this angle,
                        talking of “late eleventh-century scribal evils” in his brief study of the
                        St Nicholas-related additions to London, British Library, Cotton Tiberius B.
                            v.<hi><note place="foot" n="18">Dumville, ‘A note on the post-Conquest
                                additions’, at p. 105.</note>
                        </hi> He summarizes the bad habits of these script specimens as “lines
                        irregularly ruled,” “ill-formed and inconsistent letters,” frequent
                        tall-headed <hi>a</hi>, and frequent corrections.</p>
                    <p> In Pembroke 25 we can see many of the features described by Ker and
                        Dumville, both standard English ones and those described pejoratively as
                        “faults” common to this period. The tall <hi>a</hi>, with an extended
                        arching top part, is used often in Pembroke 25, usually at the start of
                        words as Ker specifies. The <hi>e</hi>+<hi>t</hi> ligature is found in the
                        middle and end of words, and not just to represent the word <emph>et</emph>.
                        The <hi>r</hi>+<hi>a</hi> ligature with “cc” <hi>a</hi> is frequently found,
                        as is the <hi>r</hi>+<hi>t</hi> ligature, which Ker said was “hardly found
                        after????’. The Insular <emph>enim</emph> abbreviation is found, although
                        the Insular <emph>autem</emph>, in the form of an <hi>h</hi> with a hook on
                        the right-hand side of the lower half, is not found.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi>Ker, codicology; twelfth-century two columns</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi>Insular forms to avoid clash common — other Insular habits essentially
                            tironian et</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi>probably within fifteen years each way of 1100</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi>An English scribe</hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="flyleaves">
                    <head>Added Historical content on flyleaves</head>
                    <p>Two notes, one dated 1154 and the other datable after 1153, appear on <ref
                            target="IMT/1r/1r.htm">1r</ref>–2v, in two different hands, an early
                        grand Gothic <emph>textualis precissa/quadrata</emph> and a documentary
                        cursive. These two hands may have been written by the same scribe using a
                        different cut of pen for each, since they seem to be in the same ink. Their
                        linked contents suggest that they were added on the same occasion. (For a
                        discussion of these two notes see pp. 000–000.) Probably fol. 1, the only
                        singleton in the manuscript, was added to the manuscript at this time
                        specifically to make extra blank space to contains these two items.</p>
                    <p> A third historical note, now barely legible, was added to <ref
                            target="IMT/181v/181v.htm">181v</ref>, probably in the first half of the
                        twelfth century, judging from the script. This folio is very battered and
                        has a number of worm holes and stains. It seems to have been used as a
                        paste-down at some point in the manuscript’s history, probably after this
                        note was written. The ink is now extremely faint in places. See p. 000 for a
                        discussion of the significance of this third historical note.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Context of Production</head>
                <p>The monastery at Bury St Edmunds in West Suffolk was one of the richest and most
                    important in medieval England. In addition to considerable estates, it possessed
                    the incorrupt body of Edmund, king and martyr, one of England’s most revered
                    native saints, a valuable source both of income and of religious prestige. In
                    the late Middle Ages the abbey produced notable historical writers;<hi
                        rend="sup">
                        <note place="foot" n="19">See Gransden, <emph>Historical Writing</emph>, pp.
                            380–403. The poet John Lydgate was also a Bury monk; see Knowles,
                                <emph>The Religious Orders</emph>, II.273–5.</note>
                    </hi> its abbots had an impact on the political events of the day;<hi><note place="foot" n="20">As well as the influence given by controlling
                            large estates, the abbot of Bury sat in parliament; see Knowles,
                                <emph>The Religious Orders</emph>, II.281–2 and 304. For Abbot
                            Samson, friend of Hubert Walter, the influential archbishop of
                            Canterbury during the reigns of Richard I and John, see <emph>The
                                Chronicle of Jocelin of Brakelond</emph>, ed. and trans.
                        Butler.</note>
                    </hi> and it also had a large and important library.<hi><note place="foot" n="21">Knowles, <emph>The Religious Orders</emph>,
                            II.350.</note>
                    </hi> When the shrine of Edmund was stripped in 1538, it yielded 5000 marks of
                    gold and silver plus many precious stones, and at the abbey’s surrender in the
                    following year its abbot received one of the highest recorded pensions given to
                    an ex-monastic at the Dissolution, £330 per year.<hi><note place="foot" n="22">Knowles, <emph>The Religious Orders</emph>,
                            II.270–2 and III.415.</note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Bury St Edmunds before the Norman Conquest</head>
                    <p>The abbey of Bury St Edmunds was certainly founded before the Norman
                        Conquest, but pre-Conquest evidence for its history is sparse. The evidence
                        of two wills suggests that there was a church of Edmund at
                            <emph>Bedricesworth</emph> (the original name of the place which came to
                        be known as Bury St Edmunds) in the mid-tenth century,<hi><note place="foot" n="23">The will of Ealdorman Ælfgar, datable 946×951,
                                leaves land <emph>into Beodricheswrthe to seynt Eadmundes
                                stowe</emph>: see Sawyer, <emph>Anglo-Saxon Charters</emph>, no.
                                1483; <emph>Anglo-Saxon Wills</emph>, ed. and trans. Whitelock, pp.
                                6–9 and 103–8 (no. 2). The will of Bishop Theodred, also datable
                                946×951, refers to <emph>sancte Eadmundes kirke</emph>, although it
                                does not specify where this is: Sawyer, <emph>Anglo-Saxon
                                Charters</emph>, no. 1526; <emph>Anglo-Saxon Wills</emph>, ed. and
                                trans. Whitelock, pp. 2–5 and 99–103 (no. 1). <hi>[[NB what about
                                    the Canterbury treachery one?]]</hi>
                            </note>
                        </hi> and a charter of 963 records a grant of land to “ecclesie sancti
                        Martiris sui Edmundi quæ sita est in loco celebri appellativa ruricolarum
                        appellatione at Beodrichesworth nuncupato.<anchor xml:id="_Ref147133821"
                            />”<hi><note place="foot" n="24">Sawyer, <emph>Anglo-Saxon Charters</emph>, no.
                                1213; Dumville, <emph>English Caroline Script</emph>, p. 35, n. 132;
                                    <emph>Codex Diplomaticus</emph>, ed. Kemble, II.379–80 (no.
                                491). The Bury St Edmunds archive of Anglo-Saxon charters is in the
                                process of being edited by Katherine Lowe and Sarah Foot for the
                                British Academy series of Anglo-Saxon Charters; in the interim I
                                have taken this text, and the date of 963 rather than 962, from
                                London, British Library, Additional 45951, fols. <ref
                                    target="IMT/1v/1v.htm">1v</ref>‑<ref target="IMT/2r/2r.htm"
                                >2r</ref>, which although written in the fifteenth century seems to
                                have been taken from a now-lost single-sheet.</note>
                        </hi> A dubious charter of King Edmund, dated 945, calls the church a
                            <emph>monasterium</emph>; although problematic as it stands, this text
                        is likely to have some underlying authentic basis.<hi><note place="foot" n="25">Sawyer, <emph>Anglo-Saxon Charters</emph>, no.
                                507; <emph>Codex Diplomaticus</emph>, ed. Kemble, II.258–9 (no.
                                404); Hart, <emph>The Early Charters of Eastern England</emph>, pp.
                                54–8 (no. 74); Whitelock, ‘Review’, p. 113; Hart, ‘The East Anglian
                                Chronicle’, p. 277; Hart, <emph>The Early Charters of Northern
                                    England</emph>, p. 385; Dumville, <emph>English Caroline
                                Script</emph>, pp. 35–6.</note>
                        </hi> However, all these documents are preserved only in later Bury
                        archives, and may have been altered in copying.<hi><note place="foot" n="26">Though see note [24]; Sawyer 1213 seems to survive in a copy in
                                imitative script taken directly from a now-lost tenth-century
                                original.</note>
                        </hi> Abbo of Fleury’s <emph>Passio S. Eadmundi</emph>, written while Abbo
                        was staying at Ramsey in 985–987, only mentions <emph>Bedricesworth</emph>
                        briefly, but implies that Edmund’s church was established there before the
                        death of Theodred, bishop of London, in 951.<hi><note place="foot" n="27">Ælfric’s <emph>Life of Edmund
                                    </emph>(<emph>Ælfric’s Lives of Saints</emph>, ed. Skeat,
                                I.314–35), written in the late tenth century, is on the whole a
                                direct translation of Abbo’s <emph>Passio</emph>, and his comments
                                on Edmund’s resting-place cannot therefore be interpreted as
                                implying disapproval for the community there, as has been suggested
                                (oddly enough, in a volume about the importance of source-study for
                                understanding texts; Lendinara, ‘Abbo of Fleury’, p. 4.)</note>
                        </hi> There is no mention of Bury St Edmunds in any text of the
                            <emph>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</emph> written before the Conquest,<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="28">Bury St Edmunds is mentioned in the E-version
                                of the Chronicle (from Peterborough) under the year 1046 (<emph>Two
                                    of the Saxon Chronicles</emph>, ed. Plummer, I.166), but this
                                manuscript is written in one hand down to the annal for 1121.</note>
                        </hi> and the Old English text on the resting-places of saints, probably
                        compiled in the early tenth century, says that Edmund lies at
                            <emph>Bedricesworth</emph> in East Anglia, but does not specify <emph>on
                            þam mynstre</emph> as it does in several other entries.<hi><note place="foot" n="29">
                                <emph>Die Heiligen Englands</emph>, ed. Liebermann, pp.
                            13–14.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p> Just as the date of Bury’s foundation is difficult to discover, so it is not
                        easy to tell what sort of estates Bury had in its early history; it may have
                        been a very wealthy house from the beginning, or it may have achieved
                        prominent wealth only in the reign of Edward the Confessor. In 1043 Emma,
                        who had been the lady, <emph>hlæfdige</emph>, of England since her marriage
                        to Æthelred in 1002, surviving two changes of dynasty, was deprived of her
                        lands and treasures by her son Edward the Confessor.<hi><note place="foot" n="30">
                                <emph>Two of the Saxon Chronicles</emph>, ed. Plummer, I.162. See
                                Stafford, <emph>Queen Emma</emph>, pp. 248–53.</note>
                        </hi> These included extensive liberties in Suffolk which were granted to
                        Bury St Edmunds, making it a very wealthy house.<hi><note place="foot" n="31">
                                <emph>Anglo-Saxon Writs</emph>, ed. Harmer, pp. 154–5 (no. 9).
                                Davis, ‘The Liberties’.</note>
                        </hi> It seems likely that the monastery was already well staffed by this
                        time, as this grant carried with it heavy administrative responsibilities.
                        In 1044 Leofstan became abbot of Bury, and it was probably at about this
                        time that he made the survey of some of the abbey’s possessions which
                        survives in a contemporary hand at the back of Oxford, Corpus Christi
                        College, 197.<hi><note place="foot" n="32">
                                <emph>Anglo-Saxon Charters</emph>, ed. and trans. Robertson, pp.
                                192–201 and 440–7 (no. 104). See below, pp. 14–19.</note>
                        </hi> This survey includes a list of books and vestments; some are said to
                        be in the possession of particular personnel, giving us the names of seven
                        members of the community as well as of abbot Leofstan: these are Brihtric (a
                        priest, or perhaps the prior), Blacere, Siferth, Ætheric, Thurstan, Oscytel,
                        and another Leofstan.<hi><note place="foot" n="33">This Leofstan is not the abbot, since a
                                Leofstan is said earlier in this document to have given the same
                                donation to the house as abbot Leofstan, except for ten
                            cheeses.</note>
                        </hi> Of course, there may have been further members of the community who
                        did not have any books in their possession at this time, and eight is
                        therefore a minimum number for the personnel of the abbey at this time. The
                        grant of extensive privileges in 1043 and Leofstan’s survey, probably made
                        soon after 1044, set the tone for Bury’s subsequent history, which has often
                        been seen as one of wealth and careful administration.<hi><note place="foot" n="34">Davies, ‘The Monks’.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Abbot Baldwin</head>
                    <p>In 1065, perhaps as one of his last royal acts, Edward the Confessor
                        appointed a new abbot at Bury St Edmunds, replacing Leofstan, who had been
                        there since 1044. King Edward did not choose to promote one of the Bury
                        monks; instead he set over them one of his own chaplains, a Frenchman called
                        Baldwin. (This ran entirely contrary to the right to choose their own abbot
                        which the Bury monks under Baldwin claimed had been theirs since time
                        immemorial.) Baldwin was one of several of Edward the Confessor’s overseas
                        chaplains who were promoted to high ecclesiastical office, like Giso of
                        Wells and Regenbald of Cirencester.<hi><note place="foot" n="35">Keynes, ‘Giso’, ‘Regenbald’.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <div><head>Before Bury</head>
                    <p>Our evidence for the career of Baldwin before he became abbot of Bury St
                        Edmunds comes from two sources: later hagiographical writing; and documents
                        relating to English estates granted to Saint-Denis.</p></div>
                    <div><head>Saint Denis</head>
                    <p>Temporis Anglorum regis Eduuardy medicus</p></div>
                    <div><head>His works at Bury</head>
                    <p>By the time of Domesday book Bury St Edmunds was one of the richest abbeys in
                        England, exceeded only by Glastonbury, Ely, and Christ Church,
                            Canterbury.<hi><note place="foot" n="36">In Cambridge, Pembroke College, 47, fols.
                                117–19; <emph>English Benedictine Libraries</emph>, ed. Sharpe
                                    <emph>et al</emph>., pp. 50–94. This was written by three
                                scribes, two working in the third quarter of the twelfth century and
                                the third at the turn of the century.</note>
                        </hi>Baldwin had built on the abbey’s already substantial holdings to
                        achieve this. </p>
                    <p>Reorders past</p>
                    <p>Forged charters</p>
                    <p>Privileges of abbey</p>
                    <p> Annals</p>
                    <p>Building works</p>
                    <p>Builds extra church, for which he was remembered in later centuries. Also
                        reorganises the town to encourage trade.</p></div>
                    <div><head>Hagiography</head>
                    <p> Baldwin vigorously promoted the cult of St Edmund during his time as abbot.
                        It was from the reknown of Edmund’s holy death, his incorrupt body, and his
                        subsequent miracles that the abbey derived much of its prestige. The
                            <emph>vita</emph> of St Edmund by Abbo of Fleury was an elegant
                        promotion of his sanctity by a great monastic writer, with an
                        unchallengeable authority in that it told the story of Edmund’s death as
                        related to Abbo by St Dunstan, archbishop of Canterbury, “with tears
                        streaming down his face,” as he himself had heard it as a young man at the
                        court of King Æthelstan from Edmund’s own standard-bearer. Abbo’s
                        <emph>vita</emph> had soon been translated into Old English by Ælfric of
                        Eynsham, who included it as one of only XXX English saints in his
                        collections of homiletic <emph>Lives of Saints</emph>. Edmund’s status as an
                        incorrupt saint, whose body did not rot but instead gave off the pleasant
                        “odor of sanctity,” put him in a select group of great English saints along
                        with Cuthbert at Durham and Æthelthryth at Ely.<hi><note place="foot" n="37">St Edith of Wilton was said to be partially
                                incorrupt: her lower body did not rot because of her virginity, and
                                the thumb and first two fingers of her right hand did not rot
                                because she used the to cross herselfol.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p> However, Abbo’s text was not ideal from a Bury St Edmunds point of view as
                        it does not mention where his body is to be found, and it does not include
                        many post-mortem miracles. Abbo talks of the pleasant part of England in
                        which Edmund rests, but he does not identify the specific place, and he was
                        probably referring to the wider area of East Anglia; he spent a few years of
                        exile at Ramsey Abbey and wrote the <emph>vita</emph> of Edmund at the
                        request of the monks there. The earliest manuscript of Ælfric’s <emph>Lives
                            of Saints</emph>, the only one surviving from before the Norman
                        Conquest, is London, British Library, Cotton Julius E. vii, and this
                        manuscript is used as the basis for the modern edition of these texts. It
                        specifies in the homily on Edmund that he rests at Bedricesworth
                        [<hi>sp</hi>.], the old name for Bury St Edmunds, but since this manuscript
                        was written certainly at Bury St Edmunds itself, it is impossible to tell
                        whether this detail was in Ælfric’s original text. </p>
                    <p> Baldwin therefore needed to make more of the link between Bury St Edmunds
                        and the renowned saint whose body it held. To do this he commissioned a work
                        on the Miracles of St Edmund from a monk called Hermann. This text, the
                            <emph>Miracula S. Eadmundi</emph>, was written in a complex and witty
                        Latin, and the absence of a modern edition or any translation has hindered
                        its use by modern scholars.<hi><note place="foot" n="38">I am extremely grateful to Dr Tom Licence, who
                                has generously discussed with me his forthcoming edition and
                                translation of this text for Oxford Medieval Studies; his work looks
                                set to open this very interesting material to a much wider scholarly
                                audience.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Events set in train by Baldwin continued after his death.</p>
                    <p>Promotes cult of St Edmund in England and abroad, by spreading both texts and
                        relics.</p>
                    <p>Feudal book</p>
                    <p>Develops sophisticated administrative records, to manage the abbey’s holdings
                        and defend them against the depradations of the Normans</p>
                    <p>His successors</p>
                    <p>At Baldwin’s death ...</p>
                    <p>While Baldwin himself died in January probably in 1097 but possibly in 1098,
                        the works he had set in train at Bury can be seen continuing after his
                        death. The only manuscript of the Miracula S. Eadmundi was. Although
                        Pembroke 25 may have been written after Baldwin’s death, it was certainly
                        written during the period of his influence on the abbey’s activities of
                        self-improvement.</p></div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Bury St Edmunds Library and the Significance of Pembroke 25</head>
                    <div><head>Scribal comparanda and book production</head>
                    <p>In 1953 T. A. M. Bishop suggested that one of the hands of Pembroke 25 could
                        also be seen at work in Cambridge, University Library, Ff. 2. 33 (1200),
                        fols. i, ii, vi, and vii, and in Oxford, Bodleian Library, e Museo 6
                            (<emph>S.C.</emph> 3567); unfortunately he did not specify to which of
                        the two hands of Pembroke 25 he was referring.<hi><note place="foot" n="39">Bishop, ‘Notes I’, p. 434.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p> The main part of Cambridge, University Library, Ff. 2. 33 is a
                        thirteenth-century Bury St Edmunds cartulary. Among its flyleaves are two
                        bifolia, one at each end of the manuscript, containing the <emph>Concilium
                            Africanum</emph> of A.D. 424;<hi><note place="foot" n="40">Gneuss, <emph>Handlist</emph>, p. 26 (no. 5);
                                Gameson, <emph>The Manuscripts</emph>, p. 57 (no. 21).</note>
                        </hi> these are labelled fols. i–ii and vi–vii respectively
                        (<ref>image</ref>). They are written in an elegant, smallish, and quite
                        dense Anglo-Caroline minuscule, with a slight forward slant. Palaeographical
                        dating would suggest that they came from a manuscript written in the late
                        eleventh century or perhaps the early twelfth. Since they were used in the
                        binding of the thirteenth-century cartulary,<hi><note place="foot" n="41">NB check binding of Fols. 2. 33 (the catalogue
                                is inadequate).</note>
                        </hi> the original manuscript was probably dismantled at Bury St Edmunds by
                        this date and was probably also written there.<hi><note place="foot" n="42">This manuscript is no longer in its original
                                binding, so it is possible that these flyleaves were bound with the
                                main part of the manuscript at a later date.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Oxford, Bodleian Library, e Museo 6 (<ref>image</ref>) contains Augustine’s
                            <emph>In Euangelium Iohannis</emph> and part of Possidius’s <emph>Vita
                            S. Augustini</emph>.<hi><note place="foot" n="43">Gneuss, <emph>Handlist</emph>, p. 99 (no.
                                618); Gameson, <emph>The Manuscripts</emph>, p. 136 (no.
                            717).</note>
                        </hi> This manuscript is similar in format to the flyleaves of CUL Ff. 2.
                        33; they were both laid out in two long columns densely written on large
                        pages. Bodleian e Museo 6 was given the classmark A.8 by Henry of Kirkestede
                        in the mid-fourteenth century, and is probably to be identified as the
                        volume called “Augustinus super Iohannem” in the late twelfth-century Bury
                        library catalogue.<hi><note place="foot" n="44">Sharpe, ‘Reconstructing’, pp. 213 and 208;
                                    <emph>English Benedictine Libraries</emph>, ed. Sharpe<emph> et
                                    al.</emph>, p. 79 (B13.188).</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p></div>
                        <div><head>Pembroke 25 and other Bury St Edmunds script-specimens</head>
                    <p>The script of Pembroke 25 fits neatly into a continuum of practices seen at
                        Bury St Edmunds at this time.<hi><note place="foot" n="45">For exhaustive detail on the scribal habits of
                                specimens which can be considered as definite, probable, or possible
                                Bury St Edmunds script specimens up to the first couple of decades
                                of the twelfth century, see Rushforth, ‘The Late Eleventh- and Early
                                Twelfth-Century Manuscripts’.</note>
                        </hi> That is was at Bury St Edmunds very soon after it was written is shown
                        the note at the end of the manuscript on the expulsion of clerics from Bury
                        St Edmunds (see pp. 000-000 below).</p>
                    <p>English script stayed in Bury despite those Bec monks, etc.</p>
                    <p>later word dividing marks</p>
                    <p>move to the Library section?</p></div>
                    <div><head> Existing scholarship on the library at Bury St Edmunds</head>
                    <p>The library of Bury is unusually well documented: a detailed late
                        twelfth-century catalogue survives,<hi><note place="foot" n="46">In Oxford, Corpus Christi College, 197, fol.
                                107 (‘Surviving Booklists’, ed. Lapidge, pp. 123–4 [no. VII]); and
                                in Oxford, Bodleian Library, Auct. D.2.14 (<emph>S.C.</emph> 2698),
                                    <ref target="IMT/173r/173r.htm">173r</ref> (‘Surviving
                                Booklists’, ed. Lapidge, pp. 146–9 [no. XII]).</note>
                        </hi> as well as two short booklists from the eleventh century.<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="47">Rouse, ‘Bostonus’; Sharpe,
                            ‘Reconstructing’.</note>
                        </hi> The aforementioned systematic activities of Henry of Kirkstede in the
                        mid-fourteenth century, in adding <emph>ex libris</emph> inscriptions,
                        classmarks, and contents lists to Bury books, allow the secure attribution
                        of late medieval Bury provenance to numerous manuscripts.<hi><note place="foot" n="48">Rouse, ‘Bostonus’; Sharpe,
                            ‘Reconstructing’.</note>
                        </hi> Consequently it is not surprising that the library has received much
                        attention from modern scholars. M. R. James, the great cataloguer, seems to
                        have been the first to have noticed the distinctive classmarks in Bury St
                        Edmunds books, and published his findings in two studies written at the
                        beginning and towards the end of his career.<hi><note place="foot" n="49">James, <emph>On the Abbey</emph> and ‘Bury St
                                Edmunds Manuscripts’. See also Ker, <emph>Medieval Libraries</emph>,
                                pp. xviii–xix and 16–22.</note>
                        </hi> Rod Thomson has written widely on the Bury library and archives,
                        including a detailed study of the contents, sources, and cultural
                        implications of Bury’s book collection in the eleventh and twelfth
                            centuries.<hi><note place="foot" n="50">Thomson, ‘The Library and Archives’, ‘Bury St
                                Edmunds Manuscripts’, ‘The Library of Bury St Edmunds Abbey’, and
                                    <emph>The Bury Bible</emph>.</note>
                        </hi> Richard Sharpe has edited the Bury booklists and has reconstructed the
                        library from surviving classmarks.<hi><note place="foot" n="51">Sharpe, <emph>Shorter</emph> and
                                ‘Reconstructing’.</note>
                        </hi> A survey concentrating on how Bury acquired books in the eleventh and
                        twelfth centuries has been written by Teresa Webber,<hi><note place="foot" n="52">Webber, ‘The Provision’.</note>
                        </hi> and a catalogue of Bury manuscripts now in Cambridge (a large
                        proportion of those surviving) has been written by Antonia Gransden.<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="53">Gransden, ‘Some Manuscripts’.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p> Palaeographical examination of Bury books has been less common and has
                        focused in great detail upon the twelfth century. McLachlan has published a
                        survey of the manuscripts produced at Bury in the twelfth century combining
                        palaeographical and art-historical evidence, particularly in the third and
                        fourth decades, showing that there was highly organized production at this
                        time by stable personnel.<hi><note place="foot" n="54">McLachlan, ‘The Scriptorium’ and <emph>The
                                    Scriptorium</emph>.</note>
                        </hi> The script of Bury has also been treated in passing by several of the
                        great palaeographers, notably Neil Ker and T. A. M. Bishop, in surveys
                        dealing with much broader subjects. In his <emph>English Manuscripts in the
                            Century After the Norman Conquest</emph>, Ker notes that Bury St Edmunds
                        was one of those places where English script continued to be written with
                        little Norman influence after the Conquest,<hi><note place="foot" n="55">Ker, <emph>English Manuscripts</emph>, pp. 22
                                and 35, and <emph>Catalogue</emph>, p. xxvi</note>
                        </hi> while Bishop examined the script of a late eleventh-century Bury
                        gospel book and some Bury writs.<hi><note place="foot" n="56">Bishop, <emph>English Caroline
                                Minuscule</emph>, pp. xi–xxiv, and ‘Notes II’, pp. 185–7; and Bishop
                                and Chaplais, ed., <emph>Facsimiles</emph>, p. xvii, nos. 1 and
                            2.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p></div>
                    <div><head>Importation of books from France</head>
                    <p>In the second half of the eleventh century the Bury St Edmunds abbey library
                        was augmented in a variety of ways. Books were certainly written there, but
                        they were also imported from the Continent.</p>
                    <div><head>Ninth-century French manuscripts</head>
                    <p>The ninth century, a period which saw an almost complete collapse of
                        Anglo-Saxon literary culture, was a golden age of manuscript production in
                        France. A group of manuscripts written in ninth-century Francia was probably
                        imported to Bury St Edmunds at this time. These survive as Cambridge,
                        Pembroke College MSS 17; 46, fols. 82 and 83; 81; 83; 88; 91; and 108.<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="57">Although Cambridge, Pembroke College, 308, a
                                late ninth-century Rheims copy of Hrabanus Maurus’ commentary on the
                                Pauline epistles is not from Bury as it has certain late medieval
                                provenance at Ely: see James and Minns, <emph>A Descriptive
                                    Catalogue</emph>, pp. 275–6. Oxford, Bodleian Library, Rawlinson
                                C.697 (<emph>S.C.</emph> 14853) was also written in ninth-century
                                Francia but seems to have travelled there via Wessex; Keynes, ‘King
                                Æthelstan’s Books’, p. 144 and pl. I.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Figure 1: Ninth-century French manuscripts imported to Bury</p>
                    <table rend="frame" xml:id="Table1">
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <emph>MS no.</emph>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <emph>date and place of origin</emph>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <emph>classmark</emph>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <emph>catalogue entry</emph>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <emph>further Bury connection</emph>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 17 </cell>
                            <cell>s. ix med., Tours area</cell>
                            <cell>J.6</cell>
                            <cell>Ieronimus super Ysaiam</cell>
                            <cell>s. xiii in. Bury ownership-inscription </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 46, fols. 82 &amp; 83</cell>
                            <cell>s. ix/x, N. France</cell>
                            <cell>[A.222]</cell>
                            <cell>[fragments of sacramentary, in use as flyleaves]</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 81 </cell>
                            <cell>s. ix 2/3, prob. S. France</cell>
                            <cell>B.282</cell>
                            <cell>Beda de templo et XXX questiones eiusdem in libro Regum</cell>
                            <cell>s. xiii in. Bury ownership-inscription</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 83 </cell>
                            <cell>s. ix med., Saint-Denis, Paris </cell>
                            <cell>B.287</cell>
                            <cell>Beda super Lucam</cell>
                            <cell>s. xi ex. added document about an Anglo-Scandinavian
                            funeral-feast</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 88</cell>
                            <cell>s. ix/x, Saint-Denis, Paris, or possibly England<hi><note place="foot" n="58">Gneuss, <emph>Handlist</emph>, p. 41
                                        (no. 135); Bischoff, <emph>Katalog</emph>, p. 183. Cfol.
                                        Bishop, <emph>English Caroline Minuscule</emph>, pp. xii,
                                        xxv, 5, and 18; Dumville, <emph>English Caroline
                                        Script</emph>, p. 78; Ker, ‘The English Manuscripts’, p. 77,
                                        n. 4; and McKee, ‘St Augustine’s Abbey’, pp. 96–109 and
                                        120–2.</note>
                                </hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>G.18</cell>
                            <cell>[not included; Laidcenn, excerpts from Gregory the Great,
                                    <emph>Moralia in Job</emph>]</cell>
                            <cell>s. xi ex. note on food rents probably written at Bury</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 91</cell>
                            <cell>s. ix 1/3, N. France</cell>
                            <cell>J.3</cell>
                            <cell>Ieronimus superPsalterium</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Pembroke MS. 108 </cell>
                            <cell>s. ix 2/3, East France</cell>
                            <cell>FOL.12</cell>
                            <cell>Edictum piissimi imperatoris Iustiniani</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Another manuscript probably imported at around this time survives only as
                        fols. 3–4 of London, British Library, Royal 8. F. xiv. This is an early
                        eleventh-century copy of Vergil’s <emph>Aeneid</emph> with scholia, probably
                        written in France. These folios were in use as flyleaves by the time of
                        Henry of Kirkestede, who gave the manuscript the classmark G.15. An entry in
                        the late twelfth-century Bury catalogue reads <emph>Virgilius .ij.</emph>
                        <hi rend="sup">o</hi> and these flyleaves could be the remnant of one of
                        these copies.<hi><note place="foot" n="59">
                                <emph>English Benedictine Libraries</emph>, ed. Sharpe<emph> et
                                al.</emph>, p. 70 (B13.107). The other copy might now be represented
                                by the palimpsested leaves in London, College of Arms, Arundel 30;
                                see below, pp. 65–6.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p></div>
                    <div><head>Pembroke MSS 23 and 24</head>
                    <p>Cambridge, Pembroke College, 23 and 24 are a two-volume set of homilies
                        written in France, perhaps at Saint-Germain-des-Prés in Paris, in the
                        mid-eleventh century.<hi><note place="foot" n="60">Webber, ‘The Provision’, p. 188; James and
                                Minns, <emph>A Descriptive Catalogue</emph>, pp. 20–25; Gransden,
                                ‘Some Manuscripts’, p. 254 and pl. XLVA; Gneuss,
                                <emph>Handlist</emph>, p. 40 (nos. 129–30). For plates showing
                                eleventh-century script from Saint-Germain-des-Prés see Deslandres,
                                ‘Les manuscrits’.</note>
                        </hi> The manuscripts were labeled O.52 and O.54 by Henry of Kirkestede.<hi
                           ><note place="foot" n="61">Sharpe, ‘Reconstructing’, p. 213. He also
                                added contents lists; see Rouse, ‘Bostonus’, p. 490.</note>
                        </hi> Both contain an early thirteenth-century Bury St Edmunds ownership
                            inscription.<hi><note place="foot" n="62">James and Minns, <emph>A Descriptive
                                Catalogue</emph>, pp. 20 and 22.</note>
                        </hi> In the late twelfth-century Bury library catalogue they are probably
                        identifiable with the entries <emph>Omelarium estiuale</emph> and
                            <emph>Lectionarium sanctorum</emph>.<hi><note place="foot" n="63">
                                <emph>English Benedictine Libraries</emph>, ed. Sharpe<emph> et
                                al.</emph>, p. 70 (B13.115 and 114).</note>
                        </hi> Pembroke 24 contains an addition, probably written at Saint-Denis,
                        relating to the anniversary in 1050 of the viewing of the eponymous
                            saint.<hi><note place="foot" n="64">Gransden, ‘Some Manuscripts’, p. 254.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p></div></div>
                        <div><head>Links with MSS 23 and 24</head>
                    <p>What are the links?</p>
                    <p>It is clear that the homiliary of which Pembroke 25 is the best surviving
                        representative was used widely by Anglo-Saxon homiliarists before the Norman
                        Conquest. However, the circumstances of the production of Pembroke 25,
                        during or soon after the abbacy of Baldwin and in the atmosphere of
                        intellectual renaissance resulting from his activities, may suggest that the
                        text it contains represents a reimportation of this particular homiliary to
                        England, rather than being a textual descendant of the pre-Conquest English
                        manuscripts.</p></div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Added Notes and the Pre-Conquest Past at Bury</head>
                    <div><head><ref target="IMT/181v/181v.htm">181v</ref> and the expulsion of clerics from
                        Bury St Edmunds</head>
                    <p>M. R. James transcribed what he could see in the Pembroke 25 catalogue entry.
                        By adjusting the color spectra of a digital image of this page it has been
                        possible to expand his transcription somewhat. </p>
                    <table rend="frame" xml:id="Table2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>Anno ab incarnatione domini millesimo uicesimo a passione
                            glor</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>iosi regis et martiris aedmundi centesimo quinquagesimo</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>regnante chnutone piissimo .. olizantur monachi aput</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell>scm aedmundum …atis clericis preficitur abbas Uvius</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5</cell>
                            <cell>uir prudens et modestus.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p> From its script, a Caroline minuscule of post-Conquest aspect but with a
                        number of English features, this note cannot have been added long after the
                        manuscript itself was written, in the early twelfth century at the latest.</p>
                    <p>The note talks about the foundation of Bury St Edmunds. A similar short note
                        is found in several other manuscripts.</p></div>
                    <div><head>King Henry II</head>
                    <p>The added note on <ref target="IMT/1r/1r.htm">1r</ref> and the following deed</p>
                    <p>An interesting chronological note was added on <ref target="IMT/1r/1r.htm"
                        >1r</ref> (<ref>image</ref>):</p>
                    <p>Ab origine uero mundi secundum ebraicam ueritatem . ū . c<hi rend="sup"
                        >o</hi>. vi<hi rend="sup">o</hi> .<lb/>Anno uerbi incarnati . m<hi
                            rend="sup">o</hi> . c<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. l<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.
                            iiii<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb/>Passionis uero ipsius ; m<hi rend="sup"
                        >o</hi> . c<hi rend="sup">o</hi> . xx<hi rend="sup">o</hi> .<lb/>A passione
                        sancti eadmundi ; cc<hi rend="sup">o</hi> . lxxx<hi rend="sup">o</hi>iiii<hi
                            rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb/>A translatione ipsius ; lx<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        .<lb/>Capte Anglie ; lxxx<hi rend="sup">o</hi>v<hi rend="sup">o</hi>iiii
                        .<lb/>Regnauit Willelmus rex annos .xxi.<lb/>Willelmus secundus annos
                        .xiii.<lb/>Henricus rex annos .xxx. v .<lb/>Stephanus rex annos . x<hi
                            rend="sup">o</hi> viiii<hi rend="sup">o</hi> .</p>
                    <p>This was written in a very thick black script, a heavy gothic quadrata with
                        initial letters of each line written in red ink. (The initial of the second
                        William is the exception to this; the line is slightly indented and the
                            <hi>W</hi> is black picked out in red, which suggests that this part of
                        the note was expected to be read as a continuation of the line above about
                        his father.) The script suggests a date in the second half of the twelfth
                        century, though a later date is not impossible. The date to which the note
                        refers is 1154.</p>
                    <p> This note is followed, after a few blank lines, by a deed in a
                        twelfth-century documentary hand, a very much smaller and lower-grade
                        script. This deals with the agreement made between King Stephen and his
                        nephew Henry, son of the Empress Matilda, to the effect that Henry should
                        succeed him on the throne after his death, rather than Stephen’s son
                        William. The agreement was made in late 1153, and held sufficiently that
                        Henry succeeded as Henry II in December 1154. Although these two notes are
                        written in very different hands (not necessarily by different scribes),
                        their disposal on the page together and their linked contents suggest that
                        they should be viewed as one campaign of addition.</p></div>
                    <div><head>The East of England and the Anglo-Saxon House of Wessex</head>
                    <p>The theme of these notes is clearly the celebration of the accession of Henry
                        II to the throne of England. This is an interesting thing to see in the
                        context of Bury St Edmunds, as it suggests a particular attitude to the
                        Anglo-Saxon past. Henry II was the son of the Empress Matilda, and through
                        her mother Edith-Matilda he was descended from St Margaret of Scotland, wife
                        of Malcolm called Canmore, who was the daughter of Edward the Exile, son of
                        King Edmund Ironside, son of Æthelred the Unready. At the Norman Conquest
                        Edgar the Ætheling, the surviving son of Edward the Exile, was the last
                        descendant in the male line of Alfred the Great, Edgar the Peacemaker, and
                        the other great English kings of the house of Wessex. He was briefly
                        declared King of England after Harold’s death at Hastings — the new abbot of
                        Peterborough came to Edgar the Ætheling to have his appointment confirmed at
                        this time. However, by Christmas he was no longer seen as a viable
                        alternative to the Conqueror, and his chief supporter, Ealdred, Archbishop
                        of York, had switched his backing to William. Edgar was only about fourteen
                        years old at the time, and William pensioned him off rather than treating
                        him as a continuing threat. It was when the family fled to Scotland a few
                        years later that Margaret became the unwilling bride of King Malcolm, and it
                        was through their six sons and two daughters that the Anglo-Saxon line was
                        kept alive. William the Conqueror died in 1088, leaving the throne to his
                        second son, William Rufus. On the unexpected death of the latter in 1100,
                        Henry I acted quickly to seize the English throne, while his eldest brother,
                        Robert Curthose, was away on crusade. Henry was the only one of William the
                        Conqueror’s sons born in England after his father’s coronation, and at his
                        coronation he swore to uphold the laws of Edward the Confessor against the
                        depradations made by his brother William Rufus. Within a few months of his
                        accession he had married Edith-Matilda of Scotland, the eldest daughter of
                        Margaret and Malcolm called Canmore. In recording this event, the
                            <emph>Peterborough Chronicle</emph> refers to the bride as <emph>of þan
                            rihtan ænglelandes kyne kynne</emph> (“of the rightful royal family of
                        England”). The marriage was certainly a pro-English move on Henry’s part.
                        The Norman nobles of his court certainly interpreted it this way, and mocked
                        them by calling them “Godric and Godgifu,” implying that they had gone
                        native. Their only son was known as William Ætheling, combining a Norman
                        name with an English title. He was seen as fulfilling the prophecy which
                        Edward the Confessor made on his deathbed, that a green branch would be
                        split three furlongs from its root before they were rejoined; the three
                        furlongs were interpreted as the three Norman kings William I, William II,
                        and Henry I. However, William Ætheling’s death in the wreck of the White
                        Ship in 1120 destroyed these hopes. Henry I extracted from his nobles an
                        oath of loyalty to his remaining legitimate daughter, Matilda, but after his
                        death in 1135 his nephew Stephen was crowned instead, and the country was
                        split by civil war. (Stephen’s wife’s mother was another of Margaret’s
                        daughters.) The eventual agreement that Matilda’s son would inherit instead
                        of Stephen’s represented the end of the strife recorded in the Peterborough
                        Chronicle, <emph>quote</emph>, ‘when people openly said that Christ and his
                        angels slept’. Ailred of Rievaulx, who had grown up at the court of David I
                        of Scotland, Margaret’s youngest son, wrote a history for Henry II on his
                        accession, detailing Henry’s Anglo-Saxon ancestry. The three furlongs’
                        removal of the green branch from its root could now be interpreted as the
                        three generations of William the Conqueror, Henry I, and Matilda, rather
                        than as three kings.</p>
                    <p> The East of England was strongly associated with loyalty to the Anglo-Saxon
                        royal family in the post-Conquest period. The regional revolts in the late
                        1060s, the activities of Hereward the Wake at Peterborough and Ely, and the
                        bride-ale rebellion of 1075 helped to make the East one of the hardest
                        places for William to subdue. Bury St Edmunds was relatively unaffected by
                        the martial aspects of these activities, but there are reasons to believe
                        that it was still culturally very much attached to the Anglo-Saxon past.
                        Christina, daughter of Edward the Exile and sister of Margaret and Edgar the
                        Ætheling, and Margaret’s son Edgar, king of Scotland, were both commemorated
                        in obits added to the Bury Psalter, Rome, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana,
                        Reg. lat. 12. (This parallels the obits of the family of Edmund Ironside
                        which were written into the calendar of the Crowland Psalter when it was
                        made, probably in the late 1050s or early 1060s.)<hi><note place="foot" n="65">Keynes, ‘The Crowland Psalter’.</note>
                        </hi> Bury certainly valued its Anglo-Saxon past when laying claim to lands
                        and religious prestige (see the discussion above). The note on <ref
                            target="IMT/1r/1r.htm">1r</ref> talks of time since the <emph>captae
                            anglie</emph>, the capture or seizure of England, and breaks this time
                        down into the reigns of the individual kings; this language has a pejorative
                        implication. The addition of this material celebrating the accession of
                        Henry II involved an alteration to the physical structure of the book by
                        adding at least one extra folio, which would probably have necessitated its
                        disbinding. The impulse to add this material to a holy book suggests a
                        desire to celebrate the return of a king descended from the Anglo-Saxon
                        royal line, and so connected with their own great patron St Edmund king and
                        martyr, suggesting that a sense of Anglo-Saxon nationalism survived well
                        into the second half of the twelfth century at Bury St Edmunds.</p></div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
